Okay, so in this video, we're going to
cover some risk identification tools,
some of the more
common risk identification
tools that you need to know for the exam.
Now, let's think about this.
Before we start talking about
the actual tools, first of all,
let's think about when do
we identify risks on our project.
Well, we identify risks throughout our
project.
When do we start, right at the inception
of the project.
Even before we have a signed
project charter, we're going
to start thinking about all
of the risks on our project.
In fact, even the
business case, we will start
thinking about what risks
are there on the project.
However, when do we stop identifying risks
on the project?
And the answer is, we don't.
We continue identifying risks all the way
until the end of the project.
So risk identification starts right at the
inception of the project.
and it continues all the way until the
end.
You never, never stop identifying risks on
the project.
You can stop identifying risks once the
project is closed, once
it's officially closed.
Now, what's the most common way of
identifying risks?
I mean, let's think about this.
Do we just sit down and have endless
brainstorming sessions right with our team
every week or every
other day just to sit down
and identify potential
risks on our project?
And the answer is no, that's not the only
way of identifying risk.
That's one of the ways,
which is why under data
gathering, one of the
tools is brainstorming.
I'll talk about that in a second,
though.
But the most common way of identifying
risks on a project is when you are
performing all of the other processes,
all the other processes and all the other
knowledge areas that we've been talking
about.
As you're developing the schedule,
you're going to identify.
identify risk.
As you're determining team members,
you're going to identify risk.
As you're determining raw
materials and other resources
you need, you're going
to be identifying risk.
As we're developing the schedule,
you're going to be identifying risk.
Essentially, as you're
performing any task on a
project, that's when you
identify risks on a project.
And anybody can identify risk.
You as a project manager are not the only
person that is identifying
risks on a project.
Anybody and everybody,
any stakeholder on the project,
can potentially identify
some kind of risk on a project.
So that's the most common
way of identifying risks
as you're performing any
of these are the processes.
But we've got other tools as well.
So brainstorming is one of them,
as I mentioned.
Now, a word about brainstorming.
The whole idea of brainstorming is to try
and get as many ideas as possible.
During a brainstorming session,
you're not judging anybody's ideas.
The role of a brainstorming, is not to
judge anyone's ideas.
It's to try and get as many ideas as
possible.
Now, there's a couple of side notes I want
to make here, or a couple of bullet
points, or there's a couple of these other
bullet points here.
So you might come across
these two terms, nominal group
technique and something
called a Delphi technique.
So a nominal group technique is a
continuation, if you like, of a brainstorming.
So, as I said, in a brainstorming,
you don't judge anyone's ideas.
You collect as many ideas as possible.
It's a nominal group technique where you
actually judge the ideas now.
So this is where now you're going to go
through each of the ideas that anyone came
out with, that everyone came out with,
and then we're going to discuss them,
and then we're going to vote and rank
those ideas.
So that's where you start judging.
That's where you discuss the ideas and
determine, is it a valid idea,
or Is it not a valid idea and really just
rank those ideas?
Now, ideally, it could be by a separate
team.
It doesn't have to be.
One team that's coming up with the ideas,
like the brainstorming, and then a second
team, free from bias, then could be
discussing those ideas.
Now, it doesn't have to be a separate
team, but ideally, that would be the case.
So just in case you come across that term
nominal group technique, it's taken the
ideas from a brainstorming session,
then you're voting them and ranking.
Now, you might come across this term as
well called a Delphi technique.
Various different types of Delphi
techniques.
Some of you may have heard of the term a
wide-band Delphi.
That's a type of Delphi technique as well.
But the main thing about
a Delphi technique is
that you are getting
information anonymously.
So you're gathering information from team
members anonymously.
And the whole idea
behind a Delphi technique is
to try and prevent anyone
influencing their ideas.
on someone else.
So try and prevent a situation where,
you know, one person is trying to
influence their viewpoint on someone else
or, you know, someone saying, well,
you know, someone thinking, you know,
my manager's here, my manager's saying
this, I better agree everything to what my
manager is saying.
Regardless of whether they actually agree
with what the manager is saying or not.
You're just going to agree to it.
Or I don't like this person.
I'm not going to agree to anything that
they say.
or I like this person.
I'm just going to agree to whatever they
say.
So it's to try and prevent that kind of
situation.
So you may use a Delphi technique,
such as, for example, a polling.
Polling is an example of a Delphi.
So these are a couple of ways of
identifying potential risks on a project.
Then you've got something called a
checklist, right, a risk identification
checklist, like a, I
mean, literally it's more
of a to-do list, like
a type of to-do list.
But you may develop this,
say, from historical information,
from your organizational
process asset, from OAPR.
Remember that term OPA, organizational
process asset?
Right.
Historical information.
Historical data from a prior project.
So we did a similar project before.
So what were all the risks on this prior
project?
So that may help you identify some risks
on this particular project.
So you may create a checklist.
And then interview.
Remember, what is interview?
Interviewing means sitting down with an
individual and getting their opinions,
right, or getting their ideas.
So just general conversation even,
right?
So that can help identify risks on a
project, right?
As you're going through
the project, you know,
just a general, even just
a general conversation.
You're talking to someone and,
you know, they say something like,
hey, have you heard about this,
you know, company XYZ?
I heard they might be going on strike next
week.
Well, that's the first time you've heard
of this, and they're one of your major
vendors, that might represent a risk on
your project.
Now, other tools, under
data analysis, right,
there's something
called root cause analysis.
Now, we have a separate video on root
cause, root cause analysis, cause and
effect diagram, fish bone diagram,
Ishikawa diagram, if you remember,
so that falls under the quality management
section.
But a root cause, generally,
when you're doing a root
cause analysis, you're doing
a root cause on an issue.
And an issue is something that's already
happened.
Here we talk about a risk.
So the question is,
well, how is a root cause
analysis on an issue
going to identify a risk?
Well, very simple.
Whenever you're doing a
root cause analysis, you're also
looking at, well, what
potential risks are out there?
As you're performing a root
cause on an issue, you're
looking at, well, what other
potential issues could occur?
If it's a potential issue, then that's a
risk.
And then another one here, assumptions and
constraints analysis.
So you're going to be
identifying constraints
and making assumptions
throughout your project.
Well, some of those
assumptions and constraints
could help identify a
risk on your project.
So as a very simple example.
Let's say we have to use a machine,
This machine has been shared amongst,
you know, the many different teams,
different departments, right?
So it's a big machine.
And this machine is available to us only
for two hours a day, right?
Let's say between the hours of two and
four in the afternoon.
So that's a time slot that's being
allocated to us.
So if that's a time slot that's being
allocated to us, that means then any
activity that we have planned,
that uses that machine, we need to make
sure then that those
activities are scheduled
only between the hours
and two and four every day.
So those activities, though, are dependent
on other activities.
So if those other activities are not
complete on time, then we won't be able to
perform these activities that use that
machine.
So there's a risk.
We've identified a risk on our project.
So we can only use this
machine for two hours a
day, which basically
represents 10 hours a week.
What if we need it for more than 10 hours
a week?
What if we need that machine for say 15 or
20 hours a week?
Well again, that's highlighted a risk on
your project.
Now how we actually deal with that?
That's another matter, how we actually
deal with that.
But here we're talking about risk
identification.
There's a separate section, a separate
video on risk responses.
We've identified a risk.
Now what do we do with that risk?
Right.
Now how do we deal with that risk.
So that's a separate video on actually
responding to the risk.
Here we're just talking about identifying
the risk.
So we've identified that risk.
And that risk then was based on a
constraint that we identified,
right, or an assumption that you're
making.
Now, one of the more common ways of
identifying risks then is document analysis.
And that's exactly what I
had mentioned right at the
beginning of this section,
or beginning of this video.
How do we identify risks on the project?
Well, as we're performing any of the other
processes as we're developing the
schedule, as we're developing the scope,
determining team members and developing
the budget, we could be highlighting a
risk on a project.
So that's what the document analysis
refers to.
Analyzing any documents or processes could
uncover any kind of risk any time we're
updating a document or
creating a document highlighting a
document that could potentially
highlight a risk on a project.
And then we have SWAT analysis.
There's a separate video on SWAT analysis.
SWAT stands for strengths, weaknesses,
opportunities, and threats.
That's another tool.
But as I said, there's a separate video on
SWAT.
And then you've got these other two now,
facilitation and meetings, right?
So you maybe having risk identification
meetings or risk workshops.
And so you're going to be facilitating
then these meetings, facilitating
brainstorming sessions,
facilitating like say focus groups,
that can again help identify
any risks on your project.
And these are skills.
These are, it's a tool, it's a skill set,
one of the skills, one of the key skill
sets for a project manager of facilitation
techniques.
So these are just some of the common tools
then that you may be using to identify
risks on a project, some of the common
tools that PMI talk about in Pinbok.